(upbeat music)
- Hello, everyone, and
welcome to EnglishPod.
My name is Marco.
- My name is Catherine, and today
we've got a very advanced dialogue for you.
This is all about what
we call the miracle of life.
- That's right, today we're gonna talk a
little bit more in-depth about our bodies,
about what's going on inside, and
how and where babies come from.
- That's right, so you're going
to learn very technical terms
for parts of people's bodies, men and
women, and also about the beginning of life.
- So before a baby is born,
what do you call some of these
parts and some of these things?
So let's check out today's dialogue,
and when we come back, we'll
be exploring in-depth these topics.
(upbeat music)
- Continuing with our class, today we are
going to study briefly the miracle of life.
Many of you may think you
already know how babies come to be,
but I'm sure that some of the things we will
be talking about today may surprise you.
Billy, can you turn on
the projector, please?
Thanks.
Okay, does anyone know what this is?
- Who looks like a goat head to me?
- Nice try, but this is a woman's womb,
which contains her uterus and ovaries.
The ovaries are packed
with eggs and each
month during the middle
of the menstrual cycle.
The ripest one will be sucked
up by one of the fallopian tubes.
This is called ovulation,
and the exact time of
ovulation depends on the
length of a woman's cycle.
In an average 28 day cycle, ovulation
will most likely happen between the 12th
and 15th days, counting day one
as the first day of your last period.
- That's amazing.
So each month, the
woman produces these eggs,
and then waits for
them to be fertilized.
- Actually, every woman is
already born with over 400,000 eggs.
Some will start dying off immediately,
and others are released
during her fertile period.
- What about the guys?
I know they produce sperm and stuff.
- That's right, the man's body has a tiny
factory that produces sperm 24 hours a day.
Each ejaculation will
release about 100 million
sperm, so the factory
is always pretty busy.
The sole purpose of a sperm's
life is to fertilize the woman's egg.
- So then we basically need to put one
one together so we can have babies, right?
- Yes, the man will have an orgasm during
intercourse and ejaculate sperm and semen.
Now, this is where the race begins,
and all those millions of sperm will race
and swim from the cervix through
the uterus and to the fallopian tubes.
This could take anywhere
from 45 minutes to 12 hours.
Not all of them make
it, since some of them
go the wrong way and
get lost or simply die.
Many will actually reach the egg,
but only one will
penetrate it and fertilize it.
Once this happens, the egg
instantly changes and creates
a protective shield once
the sperm is safely inside.
- And then that's it?
- Well, the egg will be fertilized
within about 24 hours of its release.
The genetic material from the sperm combines
with the genetic material in the egg
to create a new cell that
will rapidly start dividing.
The woman is not actually pregnant
until that bundle of new
cells known as the embryo.
It travels the rest of the
way down the fallopian tube
and attaches itself to
the wall of her uterus.
Any other questions?
Then let's move on.
(upbeat music)
- All right, we're back.
So very interesting, actually
this type of lecture or class
that we just saw is
very common in biology
class or anatomy class
in the US, for example.
That's right, we also
have a class called sex ed
or sexual education, and
this is all about sex and bodies
and biology that most students have
to learn before they go into high school.
- That's right, so we
actually had a previous lesson
about sex ed, we talked about contraceptives,
and while continuing on on the topic,
this is why we have this
advanced lesson now.
It is a little bit more difficult
because we have medical
terms and specific names
of parts inside of our body.
So why don't we start with the first one
when the teacher explained
about a woman's womb.
So this might look like a
very hard word to pronounce.
There's a B there, so W-O-M-B.
We don't pronounce womb, we say womb.
And this is basically where the baby
will grow when a baby is produced.
So it's a part inside a woman's
body that we also call the uterus.
Okay, so I guess the uterus is the
specific name of that area, right?
But I guess the whole thing,
kind of like the women's belly
where the baby is gonna
be, is called the womb.
- That's right.
- Okay, so now taking a look at other parts
of a woman's body, we have
the womb, we have the uterus.
Now what about the ovaries?
- So ovaries are, actually
there are two of them
in a woman's body, and ovaries are
where eggs are stored, so women have eggs.
And this is what will one day
become, in some cases, a baby.
And so they are stored in ovaries.
And when it's time to come down,
they come down through the uterus,
through these tubes to either
come out or to be met by a sperm.
- Right, and these tubes are
actually called fallopian tubes.
So a hard word, fallopian,
again, there are two of these,
one from each ovary, and they come down,
and that's basically a passageway for eggs.
- That's right, and it's
interesting because,
in English, some women that
don't wanna have any more kids,
they very, colloquially say, I have
my tubes tied, or I had my tubes tied.
- That's right, so this means a
woman has had an operation
so that she will not have
children in the future,
and her fallopian tubes are closed
off, so that eggs cannot come down.
- That's right, so this is kind of,
and now you are more or
less, if you've heard this phrase
before, now you understand
why, the fallopian tubes,
and that's what women say, tubes tied.
- Yeah, she had her tubes tied.
- All right, so now,
all of this is going on
because, well, a woman
can't potentially get pregnant,
and during this period
of time, this is when the
woman is ovulating, or
this is called ovulation.
- That's right, so ovulation is a cycle,
that means it's something
that happens again,
and again, and again,
we call it a menstrual cycle,
and it happens once,
basically it's a process
that takes 28 days, and
it's the process of an egg
coming down, and either
being fertilized or not.
- That's right, so during ovulation,
there is a certain period of time
where it's a precise for a woman
to be able to get pregnant, right?
- And now, what about
when we move on to the men?
Now, we talked about the
women's side, what about the men's?
So, basically, women have
eggs, men have sperm.
Okay, these are little,
they look like fish almost,
they swim around, and
they are past two women
through semen, and men
have, I don't know, like 10 million
of them or something crazy,
it's a huge amount of sperm.
Now, this is an interesting
thing to differentiate.
You said two things,
sperm and semen, right?
So, sperm are the little
creatures or little fish,
as you said, that swim,
and semen is kind of
actually like the liquid
that contains them.
- That's right, so it's almost not bigger
than, but it's the liquid that they come in
to basically attack an egg
and try and fertilize an egg.
And so, remember, in English,
sperm can fertilize an egg.
Seaman cannot.
- Right, and now, this is interesting,
we're talking about two fertilize.
Maybe we've heard this in
gardening or something like this,
we've heard a fertilizer, but what do
we mean by two fertilize or fertilization?
- Okay, basically, fertilization
or to fertilize something
is to, in this case, put a
sperm together with an egg.
So, to make a baby.
- That's right.
- And so, an egg that is not fertilized
will come down and will never become a baby.
Sometimes sperm, they don't find
eggs, and they just, you know, they die.
- Now, there's another interesting
word that's very related or close to this
when we say when a
man or a woman is fertile.
- That's right, so this only
applies to women, not to men.
You can say she's fertile.
That means she has eggs, her eggs come
down, and she can have a baby at some time.
But a woman who is infertile, she's
not fertile, can never have babies.
- That's right.
- So, a lot of these women adopt babies.
- Now, what about guys?
You know that some men
can't have babies as well.
Maybe their sperm is not very good or they
have some same thing, medical condition
that prevents their sperm from fertilizing.
So, you don't say that
he is infertile or not.
- No, you don't.
- What do you say?
- He is sterile.
Okay, so a woman
can be fertile or infertile.
Infertile means she cannot have babies.
If a man's semen cannot fertilize
an egg properly, he is called sterile.
- Okay, very good.
So, this is all of what's going
on inside the man's body
as well.
And we'll actually, once
they finally combine
and get together and
the sperm fertilize the
egg, we have a little
thing called an embryo.
- Okay, so obviously it doesn't
become a baby for a little while.
This is a point of contention,
a point of argument
for a lot of people because they don't, no
one agrees when a baby becomes a baby.
But basically when an egg
and a sperm come together,
they create an embryo,
which is a combination
of genetic information and
tissue and all these things.
And that starts to grow
and to become a fetus,
which will one day, one of
this born, become a baby.
- That's right, so the embryo is basically
the first stage of when
the baby is forming.
But it's not really, as
you said, this word fetus,
it's not in our dialogue, but
a fetus is actually a formed
being, sort of say, inside
a woman's body, right?
- It's growing, it's
starting to get the pieces
that it needs to become a human being,
but maybe has not fully developed yet.
So it's still inside the
woman's womb, you can say.
- Very good, okay, a lot of
interesting things going on.
Why don't we listen to our dialogue again
and we'll be back to
talk a little bit more.
(upbeat music)
- Continuing with our class, today we are
going to study briefly the miracle of life.
Many of you may think you already
know how babies come to be, but I'm sure
that some of the things we will be
talking about today may surprise you.
Billy, can you turn on
the projector please?
Thanks.
Okay, does anyone know what this is?
- It looks like a go ahead to me.
- Nice try, but this is a woman's womb,
which contains her uterus and ovaries.
The ovaries are packed
with eggs and each
month during the middle
of the menstrual cycle.
The right best one will be sucked
up by one of the fallopian tubes.
This is called ovulation and the exact time
of ovulation depends on
the length of a woman's cycle.
In an average 28 day cycle,
ovulation will most likely happen
between the 12th and 15th days,
counting day one as the
first day of your last period.
- That's amazing.
So each month the woman produces these eggs
and then waits for them to be fertilized.
- Actually, every woman is
already born with over 400,000 eggs.
Some will start dying off immediately
and others are released
during her fertile period.
- What about the guys?
I know they produce sperm and stuff.
- That's right, the man's body has a tiny
factory that produces sperm 24 hours a day.
Each ejaculation will
release about 100 million
sperm, so the factory
is always pretty busy.
The sole purpose of a sperm's
life is to fertilize the woman's egg.
- So then we basically need to put one
one together so we can have babies, right?
- Yes, the man will have an orgasm during
intercourse and ejaculate sperm and semen.
Now, this is where the race begins
and all those millions of sperm will race
and swim from the cervix through
the uterus and to the fallopian tubes.
This could take anywhere
from 45 minutes to 12 hours.
Not all of them make it since some of them
go the wrong way and
get lost or simply die.
Many will actually reach the egg
but only one will
penetrate it and fertilize it.
Once this happens, the
egg instantly changes
and creates a protective shield
once the sperm is safely inside.
- And then that's it?
- Well, the egg will be fertilized
within about 24 hours of its release.
The genetic material from the sperm combines
with the genetic material in the egg
to create a new cell that
will rapidly start dividing.
The woman is not actually pregnant
until that bundle of new
cells known as the embryo.
Travels the rest of the
way down the fallopian tube
and attaches itself to
the wall of her uterus.
Any other questions?
Then let's move on.
(upbeat music)
- All right, so this whole aspect,
we understand how the
miracle of life works, right?
This is what it's called having
babies, the miracle of life.
It's even the name of the
video we are forced to watch
when I was 12 years old and
I still have nightmares about.
(laughs)
Well, it is interesting,
it is almost a miracle
because you are basically creating
something out of nothing almost, right?
- That's right, and what's amazing about it
is that two people who
have different genetic material
and who have different experiences and
who have different parts to their bodies
that come together and create something
that's a combination of all those things.
So it's almost kind of
like a game of surprise.
We don't know what's gonna happen.
Are they gonna have red hair or green
eyes or are they tall or short or fattest?
- That's the exact thing.
Now, talking about this aspect
that you mentioned before,
it's controversial when there is life or
when if the embryo is a baby or it's not,
this is because of many
countries or cities or states
that are discussing the
legalization or not of abortions.
- That's right, so the
reason this is a problem
for a lot of people is because no one
agrees on when a fetus becomes a baby.
And so that will determine
for a lot of people
when it is okay to abort the
fetus or to kill it and when it is not.
- Right, because I've
heard that some people say,
well, in your first month, if
you've already been pregnant
for a month, the baby
already has certain parts formed
or even I think the
heart's beginning to form.
So they say, you already pregnant.
I mean, you already have a life inside you.
Well, they say, well,
no, it's actually after
two months because then
the baby has a heartbeat.
I'm not really sure about the time tables
and I'm giving you more or less a
rough outline, but this is the controversy.
- That's right.
And so it affects laws in many countries,
it affects what medical practitioners
like doctors and nurses can do.
And it's always, I think, been
an issue as long as I've been alive.
- Yeah, yeah.
Actually, the whole abortion
topic is a big political debate
between people who are
against it, who are in favor of it.
So it's very interesting.
And actually, it's still very much
illegal in many places in the world.
- Absolutely.
And it changes, I think, according
to where you are in America as well.
So some states have different laws about it
and some states are
more lenient, for example.
- And actually, this spawned
a whole new controversy
that with the emergency
pill, that basically,
if you maybe are in risk of being pregnant,
then you take this pill
in a kind of prevents
fertilization or if
fertilization occurred already,
then it kind of prevents
further growth of the embryo.
- Right, basically it's called
the emergency contraceptive
and it's taken after, you
think you might be pregnant.
So maybe if you didn't use
other contraceptives like a condom
and you think maybe one
of your eggs, as a woman,
was fertilized by sperm, it
makes you have your period.
It makes you menstruate.
That means your whole lining of your uterus
and any egg, even if it
was fertilized, comes out.
And in some cases, people
think of it as a kind of abortion.
- That's right.
- So, yeah, it's very
interesting how the more
that we understand about
medicine and about how life
works, well, there have
been advancements as well,
like contraceptives that not only
prevent unwanted pregnancies
but also prevent transmission of
diseases, sexually transmitted diseases.
But at the same time,
other things like this,
like the emergency
contraceptive and abortion
start popping up,
so, I think it's exactly.
So a very interesting topic,
as we said, controversial,
but at the same time,
very much beautiful
because we are talking about how our bodies
work and how everyone came to existence.
- And how babies are
born, everyone loves babies.
- That's right.
So, we're really interested
to get your insights,
your opinion about anything
that we've talked about today.
And if you have any other
questions or comments,
you can always reach us
at www.EnglishPod.com.
- Yeah, we hope to see you there.
And we hope this will start a
nice conversation on our website.
Remember, keep it clean.
- Yeah, that's right.
All right, so we'll see everyone there.
Bye.
(upbeat music)